<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A third letter to A person of quality being a vindication of the former, in answer to a late pamphlet intituled A discourse of the use of images, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53984</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1105</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1303</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11875857</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11875857</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50235</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53984)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50235)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 504:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A third letter to A person of quality being a vindication of the former, in answer to a late pamphlet intituled A discourse of the use of images, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ben. Griffin, and are to be sold by Randal Taylor...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Pelling.  Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>"The former" is a reference to: The antiquity of the Protestant religion.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gother, John, d. 1704. --  Discourse of the use of images.</term>
               <term>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718. --  Antiquity of the Protestant religion.</term>
               <term>Gother, John, d. 1704. --  Nubes testium.</term>
               <term>Idols and images.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50235:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50235:1"/>
            <p>A THIRD LETTER TO A Perſon of Quality, Being a Vindication of the former, IN ANSWER TO A LATE PAMPHLET INTITULED A DISCOURSE Of the Uſe of IMAGES, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>LICENSED, <hi>Auguſt the</hi> 2<hi>d.</hi> 1687.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ben. Griffin,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>Randal Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor</hi> near <hi>Stationers Hall,</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:50235:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50235:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER To a late Pamphlet Intituled a DISCOURSE Of the Uſe of Images, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SINCE I ſent you my Laſt, one of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion has been Tampering with it, as you may perceive by a late Pamphlet under this Title, <hi>A Diſcourſe of the uſe of Images in relation to the Church of</hi> England <hi>and the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>in Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</hi> Nubes Teſtium, <hi>againſt a Pamphlet entituled, the Antiquity of the Proteſtant Religion concerning Images.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Aſſoon as I ſaw the Title Page, I fancied the Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer had been tumbling over a great many old Books, to diſcover, if he could, ſome flaw in the Hiſtorical Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count I ſent you in that Pamphlet, becauſe that is the whole ſubſtance of it, nor can any man pretend to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it, but by taking that courſe. But when I read it, I found ſome reaſon to miſtruſt, that Church-Hiſtory is a thing quite <hi>out</hi> of the Diſcourſers <hi>way,</hi> and that he durſt not venture upon it leſt he ſhould <hi>Err,</hi> which would unbecome one that is Member of a Church which pretends to be <hi>Infallible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:50235:3"/>
When he thought of writing <hi>againſt</hi> me, he ſhould have Examin'd, whether the little Hiſtory I had written were True or Falſe, as to matter of Fact: That (if it were Falſe) he might have told the World where my miſtakes lay; or (if it be True) that he might have found out ſome Artifice and Shift to clear his own Church from the guilt of Innovation. For the Point is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Veneration of Images, as it is done in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, be of Primitive Practice? I undertook to ſhew the Negative; againſt the Author of <hi>Nubes Teſtium;</hi> and in order to it I proved, that in the firſt Ages of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity the Chriſtian Church had no Images at all; that it was for about the ſpace of 400 years before any Images were ſo much as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſed;</hi> that though in after Times they came to be uſed, yet it was a long time before they were uſed in Churches; that though at laſt they were ſet up in ſome Churches, yet they were ſet up for Hiſtory or Ornament ſake only; and that it was after St. <hi>Gregory</hi>'s time (that is, above 600 years after Chriſt) before any <hi>Veneration</hi> or <hi>Worſhip</hi> was allowed to be given to Images. For the making of all this to appear, I thought a more ſpeedy and effectual courſe could not be taken, then to prove it from thoſe Controverſies which were of old, firſt between Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Heathens, and then between Chriſtians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves about the buſineſs of Images. And this I did with ſo much faithfulneſs, and you ſee with ſo much Caution, that this Diſcourſer has not one word to ſay againſt me, as to that; I am ſure he has not offer'd any thing againſt me in this his Diſcourſe; nor is it a little pleaſure to me, that he hath not medled with it at all: 'Tis a ſign his Conſcience told him, the Knot was too ſtrong for him, when he durſt not go about to untie it: For as to the Evidence I produced on my ſide, the good man ſays no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in Contradiction to it; no, not a word of that in all his <hi>ſix penny-worth</hi> of Infallibility.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50235:3"/>
Inſtead of that, he has uſed all his Wits to give me great ſtore of hard words, and to ſet me at odds with the Church whereof I am a Member, as if I had not only <hi>given my ſelf a blow over the face,</hi> but had <hi>ſtruck</hi> the Church of <hi>England in the face</hi> too, like <hi>a blind Combatant, and with a Have at all,</hi> as he is pleaſed to expreſs his thoughts. Truly I am ſo blind that I cannot ſee this. As for my <hi>own</hi> face, I thank God it doth not ſmart, nor do I ſo much as feel one of my Cheeks burn. And as for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> if I have given Her the leaſt blow, I will make Her all poſſible Satisfaction when She ſhall complain: At preſent, by what I hear from Her, I do not find that She thinks I have hurt Her in the leaſt, or that She <hi>colours</hi> at all; and by and by I hope to ſatisfie the Diſcourſer too, that inſtead of <hi>Injuring.</hi> I have done her <hi>Right:</hi> in the mean time I muſt thank him for his ſingular Care and Tenderneſs of our Church.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, upon my firſt Peruſal of his Diſcourſe I did not think my ſelf obliged to take any Publick notice of it; becauſe he doth not ſo much as endeavour to baffle any of my Evidence, nor denies matter of Fact as I have related it; but manifeſtly declines the main Point under debate, and flies off to other matter; like a <hi>Wiſe</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batant that ſtrikes, not <hi>at all,</hi> but at <hi>nothing at all,</hi> and wholly <hi>miſſeth</hi> the <hi>Mark,</hi> and what could any man have done more, that gives up the Cauſe?</p>
            <p>But upon ſecond thoughts I was of another mind; not becauſe provoked to it by his Rudeneſs (which I am ready to forgive him) but becauſe I am concern'd for Truth, and the Honour of our Church. For the man has the confidence to tell the World, that our Church <hi>doth agree with the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>in the lawfulneſs of placing Images in Churches, and that an Honour or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, or even Worſhip in its kind, is neceſſarily due to them,</hi> Pag. 19. <hi>And that if I had examin'd the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of my own Church, and underſtood what Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:50235:4"/>
               <hi>teach, I would have ſoon diſcovered the vanity of my Engagement; for</hi> (ſaith he, Pag. 20.) <hi>his own Church is for an Image-Worſhip too.</hi> This is a notorious Falſhood, and looks like a malicious Inſinuation, as if our Church would preſently ſhake hands with His, did not ſome blind Combatants keep them a ſunder. The Diſcourſer might think that this would do ſomething, eſpecially in this juncture, by creating in our Diſſenters as ill an opinion of the Church of <hi>England</hi> as we have of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and he ſeems to follow the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of ſome of his brethren, not conſidering ſo much whether what he ſays be True, as whether it will ſerve a Turn, and do them ſome good by doing Us miſchief; though I hope our Diſſenters will be ſo wiſe as to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how deeply They are concern'd as well as We, to beware of Trap.</p>
            <p>For this reaſon I ſhall beſtow upon this Diſcourſe a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time, which otherwiſe would be loſt and thrown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. And firſt I obſerve how he treats me with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, that I have the misfortune to be of a Factious and Unchriſtian Temper, a multiplier of needleſs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, a blind Combatant, one that 'tis uncertain what Church I am of, this being the only thing certain, that I am <hi>no Papiſt; a Trifler; a Furious one; a ſingular Illuminate; whoſe admirable Talent is in Buffoonry,</hi> and a great deal more of ſuch language, as doth well become the mouth of one of the <hi>Hinds Calves.</hi> But you know, the ſtrain of this Generation is mightily alter'd ſince ſeven years ago, when they thought themſelves obliged by the ſingular Humanity of Church of <hi>England-men,</hi> to give them far different Characters. That it ſeems is nothing now.</p>
            <p>His great deſign is to ſhew, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>England</hi> agree in three Points, concerning 1. The Hiſtorical Uſe of Images. 2. The Commemorative Uſe of Images. 3. The Reſpect and Honour due to Images.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50235:4"/>
Now though all this be nothing to the Hiſtory which my angry Adverſary quarrels with (for that would be True ſtill, notwithſtanding all this, could he prove it) yet I am content to go along with him in his underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; and if I am not fouly deceiv'd, he has underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken an Impoſſibility; an Eſſay perhaps towards his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking to do a <hi>Miracle</hi> next: Let us ſee a little by comparing the Senſe of both Churches.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Doctrine and Practice of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> we know enough of it, and too much of all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. She has Pictures and Images (he ſays) for the Inſtruction of the Ignorant, that ſo they may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with thoſe Sacred Perſons of Patriarchs, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Apoſtles: 'Tis for <hi>this</hi> end (ſaith our Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer) they are ſet up. And is this all? How comes it to paſs then, that She has too the pretended Pictures of the moſt <hi>Holy Trinity?</hi> Is it not that people may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Inviſible, Immaterial, Incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and Infinite Deity alſo? A Rare way indeed, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for the Ignorant to conceive Right and True No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Divine Nature!</p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſays, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath Images for the <hi>Commemorative</hi> Uſe of them, to excite people to give God thanks for his favours, and to admoniſh them to Conform their Lives to ſuch Examples. Well, we quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel not about this, nor do we blame any men for looking on the Pictures of Saints to this purpoſe, eſpecially if they find it has this power upon them. But yet I muſt tell him, that this cannot juſtifie their having ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations as I mention'd before. For when God the Father is pictur'd like an Old Man with a long Beard, and all the Three Perſons are pictur'd like Three Heads up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one Body, what influence ſuch ſtrange Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions can have to excite any man to Thankfulneſs and Conformity, doth, I confeſs, paſs my poor Trifling Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to conceive.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:50235:5"/>
3. But this is not all; for the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath Images that they may be <hi>Worſhipt</hi> alſo. This is clear even from the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and the <hi>Roman</hi> Catechiſm; nay our Diſcourſer himſelf <hi>Grants</hi> it. But then to <hi>ſoften</hi> the matter he ſays two things, which I muſt a little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that you may the better underſtand the ſtate of the difference between Church and Church. 1. He tells us, That though the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teacheth, that due Honour and Veneration is to be given to the Images of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet it is not for any <hi>Divinity</hi> or <hi>Virtue that is Believ'd to be in them, for which they</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>are to be Worſhipp'd; or that any thing is to be asked of them, or any Confidence to be placed in them.</hi> But how doth he know, that this is not <hi>Believ'd?</hi> 1. I appeal to his own Conſcience, if he doth not think that Thouſands of his Communion do verily Believe it. For what elſe can be the reaſon, that one Image is ſo devoutly and ſolemnly Ador'd, rather than another? Or, why is it done in one <hi>Place,</hi> rather than in another? Or, why do ſo many Pilgrims undertake ſuch long and tireſome journeys to <hi>Loretto,</hi> and other Oratories, rather than to others, for the worſhipping of ſome ſpecial Images? What is the meaning of all this, but that poor people are taught to Believe, that there is a Divine <hi>Virtue</hi> in Images, and a greater Virtue in ſome Images, in ſome Places, then there is in others? I know this Diſcourſer ſpeaks juſt as the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> did; for 'twas there defined, that there is no Divinity or Vertue in Images for which they ſhould be Worſhipped, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. But then I ask him, Secondly, how he knows, that the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> it ſelf was in good earneſt? Or, that their mind really was, that men ſhould not believe any Vertue to be in Images, eſpecially if they be <hi>Conſecrated?</hi> I am ſure there is good reaſon to believe, that their Definition was only a Copy of their Countenance, to ſtop the mouths of a clamorous World. And for your ſatisfaction I will
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50235:5"/>
refer you to a very Learned Author, whom this Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer hath done me the ſingular favour to call my <hi>Good Friend,</hi> meaning that Eminent Perſon Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet.</hi> I heartily thank him for entitling me to the friendſhip of ſo Great a Man, and very thankfully own his <hi>friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> ſincerely acknowledging my ſelf Beholding to him, as for ſome private favours, ſo eſpecially for his Learned Works, whereby he has be friended us all; and I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wiſh that this Diſcourſer would ſuffer him in that reſpect to be a good Friend to <hi>Him</hi> too. To that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſeeing he has ſingled out Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> as my good friend, I will deal with him at preſent out of a Book of my Friends which I have by me, deſiring the Doctors leave, that I may mention him under the character of my <hi>Good Friend.</hi> And as to the ſincerity of the men at <hi>Trent</hi> in this particular, I would fain ſee how my Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary can defend it, after what has been ſaid by my <hi>good Friend</hi> touching the <hi>Publick Acts</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church at the <hi>Conſecration</hi> of Images, eſpecially <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Defence p.</hi> 640. <hi>&amp; ſeg.</hi>
               </note> at the Conſecration of a <hi>New Croſs,</hi> and thoſe little waxen Images called <hi>Agnus Dei's.</hi> For, are not theſe Conſecrations for the procuring of <hi>Virtues</hi> to thoſe Images, and that people may receive <hi>Benefits</hi> by worſhipping of them, by means of thoſe Virtues? If this Diſcourſer underſtands his own Church, he cannot but know this to be True, and if he be ingenuous he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny it. For at the Benediction of a New Croſs there is this Prayer in the Pontificale, and he may find it Tranſcribed and Tranſlated by my <hi>good Friend; We pray thee, O Holy Lord, Father Almighty, Everlaſting God, that thou wouldſt vouchſafe to Bleſs this Wood of thy Croſs</hi> (obſerve the expreſſion, <hi>hoc Lignum crucis tuae,</hi> this Wood of thy Croſs) <hi>that it may be a wholeſome Remedy to mankind, a ſtrengthener of Faith, an increaſer of good Works, the redemption of Souls, a Comfort, Protection and</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:50235:6"/>
               <hi>Defence againſt the cruel darts of Enemies, And again, let this Wood be ſanctified in the name of the Father, and Son, and Holy Ghoſt; and let the bleſſing of that Wood, on which the Holy Members of our Saviour did hang, be in this Wood, that ſuch as Pray and Bow themſelves down for Gods ſake before this Croſs, may find Health of Body and Soul.</hi> Beſides this, in the <hi>Ceremoniale Romanum</hi> there is this Prayer, among others, at the Conſecration of the <hi>Agnus Dei's; Do thou vouchſafe to Bleſs, to Sanctifie, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate them, that being ſanctified by thy abundant benediction they may receive the ſame Virtue againſt all the Diabolical Wiles and Frauds of the Evil Spirit, that no Tempeſt may prevail againſt ſuch as devoutly carry them with them, that no Adverſity, no Peſtilence, no Corruption of the Air, no Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Sickneſs, no Storms at Sea, no Fire, no Sin may have power over ſuch, as carry theſe Images and Worſhip them.</hi> Now can any man conceive after all this, that no Virtue is believed to be in any Images, when it is ſo expreſly prayed for, that it may be given to them? Can we imagine, that the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> would have men be perſwaded contrary to what is ſaid in the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Offices of the Church concerning the Virtue of theſe Images? Or that the Pope, who owns that Council, and whoſe buſineſs it is to Conſecrate theſe things after this manner, doth believe it was the Councils meaning to deny all virtue in Images?</p>
            <p>To this I will add out of my <hi>good Friend</hi> an Admirable Piece of Infallible Poetry, which Pope <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the <hi>Fifth</hi> ſent to the <hi>Greek</hi> Emperor with Three <hi>Agnus Dei</hi>'s; partly, becauſe they ſhew the Popes opinion of the wonderful Virtues of theſe Images; and partly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſuch extraordinary Verſes for Language, for Numbers, for Fancy, and for Rhime too, that they ought to be kept in ſome <hi>Theſaurus Poeticus</hi> among ſome <hi>Pia Hilaria</hi> in the Vatican, made by his Holineſs himſelf; for neither <hi>Virgil,</hi> nor any other old Prophane Poet, no
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50235:6"/>
not the <hi>Sibylls</hi> themſelves ever did the like; and I will tranſcribe them in hopes that for the Honour of it ſome Sanctified friend of the <hi>Hinds</hi> may attempt an Imitation of them in Engliſh.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Balſamus &amp; munda cera cum Chriſmatis unda,</l>
               <l>Conficiunt Agnum; quod munus do tibi magnum:</l>
               <l>Fonte velut natum per Myſtica Sanctificatum.</l>
               <l>Fulgura de ſurſum depellit, omne malignum</l>
               <l>Peccatum frangit, ut Chriſti Sanguis; &amp; angit.</l>
               <l>Pregnans ſervatur, ſimul &amp; partus Liberatur:</l>
               <l>Dona defert dignis, Virtutem deſtruit ignis;</l>
               <l>Portatus munde de fluctibus eripit unde.</l>
               <l>Morte repentina ſervat Sataneque ruirâ.</l>
               <l>Si quis honoret eum, retinet ſuper hoſte Tropheum,</l>
               <l>Parſque minor tantum tota valet integra quantum.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>To all which my good Friend ſubjoyns a remarkable Paſſage out of <hi>Azorius,</hi> their great Caſuiſt, that it is not to be Queſtion'd, but the Pope himſelf having made Prayers over theſe Images, they will have the effects prayed for, if they be uſed with that due Reverence and Devotion which is required. And perhaps there is ſcarcely a true bred Romaniſt in the World that Queſtions it; which is the Reaſon of that wonderful opinion and value they have of them, and of thoſe ſuperſtitious Uſes they put them to; and if my Adverſary be ſuch, his denying of Virtue to be in Images can be nothing but <hi>Art,</hi> to create in people at this critical juncture a favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and kind opinion of Popery, by <hi>ſoftning</hi> a matter that is ſo offenſive, and by blinding mens eyes till they get their Noſes under their Girdles. But if he were in ſome foreign Parts, he might have as little thanks, as Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> hath had, for putting a New Face upon Holy Church, as if he were aſhamed of the good Matrons Warts and Wrinkles.</p>
            <p>2. To ſoften the matter more yet, this Diſcourſer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuates,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50235:7"/>
Secondly, that the Worſhip given by them to Images is nothing but an Honorary <hi>Reſpect</hi> and <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence,</hi> which other Chriſtians give to the word of God, to the Sacrament, to the Communion. Table, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſays the Church of <hi>England agrees</hi> with the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and therefore he blames me for running it down under the name of Image-Worſhip, without exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining the doctrine of mine <hi>own</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>For the clearing of this I ſhall briefly do theſe three things. 1. Shew what that Worſhip is which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is given to Images. 2. How far the Church of <hi>England</hi> differs from them in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. 3. I ſhall conſider the Proofs he brings of this pretended Agreement: And when this is done I hope you will be ſatisfied, that I have not ſpoken againſt Image-Worſhip without good grounds and conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What that Worſhip is which according to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is given to Images. For the right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding whereof it is to be noted: 1. That there is a great deal of difference between <hi>Worſhip,</hi> properly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and that which we call <hi>Reverence</hi> and <hi>Reſpect.</hi> All mankind, eſpecially Chriſtians have ever made a vaſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between theſe things: And it deſerves this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſers conſideration, that no leſs a man then <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> condemning thoſe to be <hi>Idolaters,</hi> who worſhip't the Holy Virgin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> expreſly ſaid, that <hi>Mary is to be Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but God to be Worſhipped,</hi> and that <hi>no man is to Worſhip the bleſſed Virgin.</hi> The Second Council at <hi>Nice</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves acknowledg'd this diſtinction; and ſo have all the Divines of the preſent Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when they have endeavour'd to prove, that Images are not only to be <hi>Honoured, Reſpected,</hi> and <hi>Reverenced,</hi> but to be <hi>Adored</hi> too. Therefore this doughty Divine, the Diſcourſer, is not a little <hi>out</hi> in <hi>Confounding</hi> things that are ſo evidently <hi>Diſtinct:</hi> For that which all the World ſaith is <hi>Worſhip,</hi> he ſays is only <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Reſpect,</hi> the ſame <hi>thing</hi> by whatſoever
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50235:7"/>
               <hi>Name</hi> it be expreſs'd: and whether you call it <hi>Honour,</hi> or <hi>Worſhip,</hi> or <hi>adoring;</hi> or whether it be ſaid to be <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary, Religious,</hi> or <hi>Divine;</hi> or whether it be deemed <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute,</hi> or <hi>Relative</hi> (worſhip) 'tis it ſeems equally alike to <hi>Him:</hi> For in his opinion 'tis only wrangling about <hi>Names,</hi> a Diſpute about a <hi>Word; fine Notions, and pretty entertainments for School-debates, but no concern of Religion or Conſcience,</hi> as he tells us, <hi>Pag.</hi> 24, 25. 'Tis pity the man was not born long ago to inſtruct the World better: for we <hi>Trifling Proteſtants</hi> have ever thought with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Chriſtians, that to <hi>Reſpect</hi> the Picture of Chriſt is one thing, and to <hi>Adore</hi> it is another; that to Bow down to it is more than to ſet it up, that to lye proſtrate before it is more then to keep it clean; and that there is a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium between tearing it in Pieces, and honouring it with Kiſſings and Bowings, and Genuflexions, and Praying before it, and offering up Lights and Incenſe and the like: We ever thought, that Divine <hi>Worſhip</hi> was to be given to God alone, that it was no <hi>needleſs</hi> contention whether the Honour due to God is to be given to the work of mens hands; and that this was a great caſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Religion and Conſcience:</hi> but it ſeems all this is <hi>nothing</hi> upon the matter; 'tis but a little ſort of <hi>Reſpect;</hi> and you know what <hi>She</hi> is, that after ſhe has been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful to her Husband, <hi>wipes her mouth</hi> as if ſhe had done no harm; and ſo the <hi>lewdeſt</hi> woman may excuſe her ſelf, that what ſome Folks calls <hi>Adultery,</hi> is nothing but a <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute</hi> about a <hi>Word, a fine Notion, a pretty Entertainment,</hi> but no concern of <hi>Religion or Conſcience.</hi> 2. That Reſpect which is given to things Sacred conſiſts in a <hi>Decent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> of them, and in uſing them after a <hi>different manner</hi> from other things. But <hi>Worſhip</hi> is quite another thing, <hi>viz. A profeſſing our ſubjection to the Object of our adoration upon the ſcore of his Dominion and Power over us as our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior;</hi> and when either the <hi>Nature</hi> of ſuch adoration, or the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of it argue it to be <hi>Religious,</hi> it is then
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50235:8"/>
Religious or Divine Worſhip, peculiarly belonging to God, becauſe it is a Token of our Abſolute Subjection to him, as having Supream and Abſolute Soveraignity over all. The greateſt men in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have had this Notion of Divine-Worſhip; and had this wonderful Diſcourſer underſtood or conſider'd it, he could not have been ſo very <hi>Indifferent</hi> about this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; becauſe the Diſpute is, not about <hi>Words</hi> but <hi>Things,</hi> and things of very great Concernment; <hi>viz.</hi> Whether ſuch actions and geſtures as are due to God, and by the Divine Law are appropriated to God, and in the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mankind, are Teſtifications of Gods Supream and Abſolute Dominion, may be perform'd to and before a dumb Image? Now this is that which we charge upon the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that there are hardly any external acts of Religious Worſhip, but what She performs to God and to Images in Common, and that according to Her doctrine Images are truly and properly to be Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, with Worſhip taken in a ſtrict Senſe, and as it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh't from, and ſignifies a great deal more than bare Honour, or Reſpect, or Reverence.</p>
            <p>For the clearing of this, becauſe it is a great Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie between my angry Adverſary and Me, I ſhall at preſent trouble him only with ſome ready obſervations out of my good Friend; and when he has anſwer'd them I promiſe faithfully to furniſh him with more.</p>
            <p>Theſe obſervations are 1. Concerning the Worſhip given by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to Images in General. 2. Concerning the Worſhip given to the Croſs of Chriſt in Particular.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Worſhip given by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to Images in general, is True and Real Worſhip; Worſhip that is a great deal higher than Reſpect or Reverence; Worſhip in a proper and ſtrict Senſe; Worſhip that doth conſiſt not only in the External Acts of Divine Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but alſo in an inward affection which implies ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50235:8"/>
as Cardinal <hi>Lugo</hi> doth confeſs. This my Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Author ſhews to have been the thing intended both by the Second Council at <hi>Nice,</hi> and by the men at <hi>Trent,</hi> who appealed to that Council; that the moſt eminent Divines in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> thought ſo, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly maintain'd it as an Article of Faith wherein all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks agree, that true and proper Worſhip is to be given not only to the Exemplars repreſented by Images, but alſo to the very Images themſelves, as <hi>Suarez, Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Tannerus, Yſambertus,</hi> and others do poſitively af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm. And leſt this ſhould be thought to be the Senſe of a few private men only, he further ſhews that ſome great Divines, who were at the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and could not but underſtand the Senſe of that Council, ſay the ſame thing. For ſo <hi>Dominicus Soto determines,</hi> that Images are not intended by the Church only for helps to memory, but for <hi>Worſhip.</hi> And whereas our Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer would make us believe that this Worſhip is no more but that <hi>Reſpect</hi> which is ſhewn to the <hi>Bible,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Soto</hi> doth utterly <hi>Reject</hi> this; for, ſaith he, <hi>We do not Worſhip the Scriptures or Names of Saints which call them to our minds; but as to Images we ought to think otherwiſe, for they do not only raiſe our minds to worſhip thoſe who are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented by them,</hi> ſed eaſdem ipſas debemus adorare, <hi>but we ought to worſhip the Images themſelves.</hi> So likewiſe <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clantus</hi> another great Man at <hi>Trent,</hi> tells the World, that 'tis a needleſs caution for any to ſay, that they worſhip before the Image, <hi>ſed &amp; adorare imaginem ſine quo volue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſcrupulo,</hi> but men may ſay it roundly and without any ſcruple, that they worſhip the Image. With theſe <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſius Catharinus</hi> agrees too, that <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Real</hi> worſhip is required to be given to Images, and concludes that I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages are not meerly for inſtruction, or memory, exciting devotion, but that they are ſet up <hi>properly</hi> for <hi>worſhip.</hi> 
               <q>Therefore if any man asks another, are Images to be worſhipped, let him, ſaith he, anſwer without any
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50235:9"/>
fear, <hi>They are;</hi> becauſe Images being ſet apart by the inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt for ſuch a Sacred uſe, do obtain ſuch a degree of Sanctification, that whoever violates them is guilty of Sacriledge and Treaſon againſt the Divine Majeſty; becauſe God himſelf is moſt truly believed to be preſent in them after a particular manner, and he ſhews his power and preſence by them, uſing them often for Oracles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If this be not enough to convince my Adverſary of the vanity of his pretences, there is one obſervation more which deſerves his conſideration; <hi>viz.</hi> That whereas ſome of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, as <hi>Durandus, Holkot,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers taught, that Images ought not to be worſhipped with the ſame worſhip with the thing repreſented, but were ſaid to be worſhipped improperly and abuſively, becauſe at their preſence men did call to mind the objects repreſented by them, which are worſhipped before the Images, but not properly the Images themſelves; this opinion was lookt upon as <hi>Heretical;</hi> and therefore <hi>Suarez</hi> and many other eminent men diſputed hotly againſt that opinion, as being contrary to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which is, that an Image is not only the <hi>occaſion</hi> or <hi>ſign</hi> exciting men to worſhip the thing repreſented, but even the material <hi>Object</hi> to which the act of Worſhip, and the <hi>Intention</hi> of the worſhipper is to be directed and carried; and which ought to be worſhipped with the <hi>ſame</hi> worſhip with the <hi>Exemplar</hi> it ſelf. And certainly <hi>Ariaga</hi> was in the right, when urging this to be the ſenſe of the Church he uſed this ſtrong Argument to prove it; becauſe it is not credible, <q>that if this had been all the Councils had determined <hi>(viz.</hi> That Images are not the objects of Worſhip, but only the occaſions and means exciting men to worſhip the Exemplars) they ſhould never think of ſuch an eaſie way to ſatisfie Diſſenters, as the declaring of this would have been.</q> But, ſaith he, the Controverſie lay in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50235:9"/>
another Point; namely, that Images did not deſerve im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate worſhip; and then he concludes, that when the Fathers condemned thoſe for Hereticks who denied that worſhip, they did not determine that Images might be uſed as a condition of worſhip, but that <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Real</hi> worſhip was to be given to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Concerning that worſhip which is given to the <hi>Croſs</hi> of Chriſt in particular, 'tis notorious that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the common received Doctrine of the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> not only Inferiour Religious Worſhip, but that which they call <hi>Latria,</hi> meaning <hi>Supream, Divine, Soveraign</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip properly due to God himſelf, is to be given to the Images of Chriſts <hi>Croſs.</hi> My Adverſary is horribly net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and upbraids me with an hard Forehead in charging him with a notion of <hi>Invocating</hi> Images, when he ſays he has no ſuch <hi>word</hi> or <hi>hint</hi> (I ſuppoſe he means in his <hi>Nubes Teſtium.)</hi> What notions he may have of this, or what he does in his private Oratory I cannot tell; nor did I charge <hi>Him</hi> in particular with <hi>Invocating</hi> Images. But this I do charge upon the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in general, that She doth formally <hi>Invocate</hi> and pray to the Images of Chriſts Croſs, and that the worſhip of <hi>Latria</hi> is, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Doctrine of her greateſt Divines, to be given to them. He cannot but know, that this form of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is uſed by that Church, and that it is directed to the <hi>Wood</hi> of the Croſs, <hi>O crux ave, ſpes unica, auge piis juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, reiſque dona veniam,</hi> Hail O Croſs, our only Hope, increaſe Righteouſneſs to ſuch as are pious, and give par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to ſuch as are guilty. For this Practiſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church was the true <hi>Ground</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> of that opinion, that <hi>Latria</hi> is due to the Image of the Croſs. This my <hi>good Friend</hi> hath ſhewed long ago, that it was one of the grounds which <hi>Aquinas</hi> went upon, when he determined <hi>Latria</hi> to be due to the <hi>Croſs,</hi> becauſe the Church in praying to the Croſs ſpeaks to it as if it were Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; <hi>O crux ave, ſpes unica, &amp;c.</hi> And more Authors there are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50235:10"/>
which ſay the ſame thing; as <hi>Marſilius ab Ingen,</hi> who aſſerts that the Croſs as a ſign repreſenting the object of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and as a Medium of it, is to be adored with <hi>Latria;</hi> and the reaſon he fetcheth from the practice of the Church, <hi>O crux ave, ſpes unica, auge, &amp;c.</hi> So <hi>Catharinus</hi> ſaith: <q>That the opinion of thoſe who ſay Images are not truly and properly to be worſhipped, but God to be worſhipped before an Image, is repugnant to the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Church, becauſe we direct our geſtures, our words and ſigns of adoration to the Images, to which likewiſe we burn Incenſe; and we worſhip the Croſs, ſaying, <hi>O crux ave, ſpes unica, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> So likewiſe <hi>Dominicus Soto,</hi> we ought to worſhip the Images them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; for the Church doth not ſay, we worſhip thee, O Chriſt, but thy Croſs; and <hi>O crux ave, ſpes unica, &amp;c.</hi> In like manner <hi>Phil. Gamachaeus,</hi> a Doctor of the <hi>Sorbon</hi> ſaith, that the Croſs and Image of Chriſt as they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him, ought to be worſhipped with the Supream worſhip of <hi>Latria;</hi> becauſe Chriſt himſelf is the reaſon of the adoration, and becauſe the Church doth ſo worſhip the Croſs, <hi>O crux ave, ſpes unica, &amp;c,</hi> Beſides all this we are told a remarkable Story of one <hi>John Egidius</hi> Canon of <hi>Sevil,</hi> that he was forced to make a publick Recantation for denying the adoration of the Croſs, becauſe it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the practice of the Church, when it ſaith, <hi>O crux ave, ſpes unica, auge piis juſtitiam, reiſque dona veniam?</hi> And after all this let this wonderful Diſcourſer tell us, whether theſe things be not True? And whether theſe things be not acts of <hi>Latria?</hi> And whether abundance of Divines more, both before and ſince the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> have not maintained this <hi>Latria</hi> to be due to the Image of the Croſs? And whether this <hi>Latria</hi> be not much more than common <hi>Reſpect</hi> and <hi>Reverence?</hi> And whether any Church of <hi>England</hi> man, or any Proteſtant ever pretended to give ſuch a ſort of Reſpect to the Communion-Table, or to the Sacramant, or to the Name of Jeſus, or to the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50235:10"/>
Bible, ſo as upon his knees to pray to it, <hi>Spes unica, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge piis juſtitiam, reiſque dona veniam?</hi> Either the man underſtands not that which he calls the doctrines of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks ſo well as We Proteſtants do, or elſe he is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſhameful diſingenuity for diſguiſing and diſſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling things thus out of a ſiniſter deſign, and then for flying upon <hi>Me,</hi> as if I had done the Innocent Papiſts wrong, by making more noiſe, and raiſing more duſt about their Worſhipping of Images, then there ought to be.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Since he hath ſo palpably miſrepreſented the ſenſe of his <hi>own</hi> Church, 'tis madneſs to conceive that he would rightly repreſent the ſenſe of <hi>Ours;</hi> which I ſhall now in the next place conſider, to ſatisfie you that I have done our Church no wrong, which is another thing he lays to my charge. Alas good man<hi>!</hi> how careful is he, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> may not be injured.</p>
            <p>For the clearing of this too, I ſhall refer you to our Book of Homilies, becauſe without all queſtion it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the publick ſenſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which he may be ſure we well know, as <hi>blind combatants</hi> as we are, and which we will with all our Zeal and Abilities defend, what <hi>Triflers</hi> ſoever he takes us to be.</p>
            <p>The particular Homily I intend is that againſt peril of Idolatry, conſiſting of three parts. And becauſe I am willing to prevent an objection which may be made by this Diſcourſer out of our Learned <hi>Mountague, viz.</hi> that he admitted the Book of Homilies, as containing godly and wholeſome exhortations, but not as the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick dogmatical reſolutions confirmed of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> therefore I ſhall offer theſe Five things briefly to your conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the former Book of Homilies in the time of K. <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth was ſet out as the Homilies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and as godly and wholeſome Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons containing Doctrine to be received of <hi>all</hi> men,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50235:11"/>
               <hi>doctrinam ab omnibus amplectendam,</hi> as appears by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle concerning it, <hi>Anno</hi> 1552. 2. That the Second Book of Homilies (wherein this againſt peril of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try is one) was alſo judged to contain godly and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Doctrine, as well as the <hi>former</hi> Book, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was appointed to be read as the former was, in all Churches diligently and diſtinctly: Which plainly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, that it was ſet out alſo in the name of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and as containing Doctrine to be received of all, as the other was judged to contain. 3. This par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Homily whereof I now ſpeak, was upon a point of National concernment, and in the judgment of our Church about a moſt important caſe of Conſcience: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it was conceiv'd and penn'd upon the greateſt conſideration and judgment, as we find by that variety of choice Learning in it, beyond what is to be found in all the Homilies beſide: And 'tis remarkable too, that 'twas intended not only for the information of <hi>the people,</hi> but alſo for the inſtruction of <hi>Curates themſelves, and men of good underſtanding,</hi> as appears by the Title of the Third Part of it. So that if any <hi>other</hi> may, yet <hi>this</hi> Homily cannot be thought a meer <hi>popular</hi> Sermon (for it is not ſo <hi>popular)</hi> but rather the <hi>Deciſive</hi> and <hi>dogmatical reſolution</hi> of our Church in this Caſe about Images. 4. As the Learned <hi>Mountague</hi> doth not deny, but that this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily contains the publick ſenſe of our Church, ſo he doth reſt in this, that it contains a godly and wholeſome Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, neceſſary for thoſe times; meaning the times in which, and for which, this Homily againſt Images and the peril of Idolatry, was ſpecially made: And if He thought it godly, wholeſome, and neceſſary, he could not but think it <hi>True.</hi> 5. Therefore I ſhall conclude, that this Homily ought to be appealed to in this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie with the Diſcourſer, as the Homily that contains the deliberate and ſetled judgment of our Church, and ſuch Doctrines as are neceſſary for theſe our times, as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50235:11"/>
well as for thoſe when it was firſt written.</p>
            <p>Now in the beginning of the Firſt part of this Homily our Church roundly tells us, that the bringing in of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges into the Church in thoſe latter days, hath nothing at all profited ſuch as were wiſe and of underſtanding, but hath greatly hurt the ſimple and unwiſe, occaſioning them thereby to commit moſt horrible Idolatry. Then having noted that the words <hi>Idol</hi> and <hi>Image</hi> are of the the ſame ſignification in the Scriptures, ſhe proves by ſeveral Texts out of the Old Teſtament and the New, that Images are neither to be Worſhipped, nor ſo much as <hi>uſed</hi> or <hi>had</hi> in Churches, for fear and occaſion of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping them, though they be of themſelves things <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different:</hi> for ſo ſhe deſires to be always underſtood to ſpeak not only againſt Idolatry and Worſhipping of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, but alſo againſt Idols and Images <hi>themſelves,</hi> in caſe men be ſtirred and provoked by them to Worſhip them, and not as though they were ſimply forbidden without ſuch occaſion and danger, as you may ſee in the beginning of the Third Part of that Homily.</p>
            <p>In the Second part ſhe gives an Hiſtorical relation of the riſe and progreſs of Image-Worſhip in the Chriſtian Church; the ſum whereof is this, <q>That Images and Image-worſhipping were in the Primitive Church, (which was moſt pure and uncorrupt) abhorred and deteſted, as abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable and contrary to true Chriſtian Religion. And that when Images began to creep into the Church, they were not only ſpoken and written againſt by godly and Learned Biſhops, Doctors and Clerks, but alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by whole Councils of Biſhops and Learned men aſſembled together; yea, the ſaid Images by many Chriſtian Emperours and Biſhops were defaced, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and deſtroyed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> And I freely leave to all men of knowledge and integrity to judge, whether in that Hiſtorical account I ſent you, there be any thing which is inconſiſtent either with the Doctrine of our Church
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50235:12"/>
as to Images and Image-worſhip, or with the Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal account which our Church her ſelf gives us. I think indeed there is an obſervation which our <hi>Church</hi> there makes, but <hi>I</hi> did not; <q>That the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> being no ordinary Magiſtrates appointed of God out of their Dioceſs, but Uſurpers of Princes Authority, contrary to Gods word, were the maintainers of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges againſt Gods word, and ſtirrers up of Sedition and Rebellion, and workers of continual Treaſon againſt their Soveraign Lords, contrary to Gods Law, and the ordinances of all humane Laws, being not only Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to God, but alſo Rebels and Traitors againſt their Princes. Theſe were the firſt bringers in of Images openly into Churches. Theſe were the maintainers of them in the Churches; and theſe were the means whereby they maintain'd them, to wit, Conſpiracy, Treaſon and Rebellion againſt God and their Princes.</q> As I remember I did not obſerve this, at leaſt not ſo ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but if that be a fault, I ſuppoſe this Diſcourſer will readily forgive it: If not, 'tis an even lay, but ſome other time I may make him amends.</p>
            <p>In the Third Part of this Homily our Church doth purpoſely anſwer thoſe allegations and pleas which are commonly uſed by the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> to excuſe and juſtifie their practice in this point: as, <hi>that their Images are not of any Heathen Idols, but of God, of Chriſt and his Saints; that the making of Images is a thing in it ſelf indifferent; that they exhibit Honour not to the Image, but to exemplar repreſented by it; and that Images are lay-mens Books:</hi> And throughout this long Sermon our Church declares her ſenſe. <q>1. That the Images of God the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt are unlawful to be made. 2. That though the Art of painting and Image making be not wicked of it ſelf, and ſuch Images may be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as are uſed for no Religion, or Superſtition ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (ſhe means of none Worſhipped, nor in danger
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50235:12"/>
to be Worſhipped of any) yet conſidering the great danger of Idolatry, and the ſtrong inclinations of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to it, Images are not to be publickly had and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in Churches: Which danger ſhe ſhews at large, becauſe all Images publickly ſet up have been worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, not by the ſimple ſort only, but in concluſion by the Learned alſo; and becauſe ſhe conceived it impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that Images of God, Chriſt, or his Saints can be ſuffered, eſpecially any conſiderable time or ſpace, without Worſhipping of them. 3. She ſhews, that the Saints neither deſire nor ought to be Honoured by Images; that the diſtinction of <hi>Latria</hi> and <hi>Dulia</hi> is a lewd diſtinction; that the pretence of honouring the Prototype by the Image is an old Heathen ſhift; and that though it be ſaid, that the Honour is given to the Prototype, yet this is only to palliate the matter; for our Church evidently proves that the Papiſts did Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Images themſelves, not only by ſhewing their groſs and Pagan-like Idolatry in that reſpect, but alſo by producing the Authority of <hi>Jacobus Naclantus</hi> (an Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Divine in the Council of <hi>Trent)</hi> that it is not only to be confeſt that the faithful in the Church do worſhip before an Image (as ſome peradventure do warily ſpeak) but alſo do Worſhip the Image it ſelf, without any ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or doubt at all; yea, and they Worſhip the Image with the ſame kind of Worſhip, wherewith they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Prototype; wherefore if the Prototype be to be worſhipped with Divine Worſhip, the Image is alſo to be worſhipped with the ſame.</q> 4. Having abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſhew'd the Snares, and dangers which Images draw people into, and the vaſt miſchiefs and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes they occaſion, inſtead of inſtructing men like Books, our Church at laſt plainly reſolves the point, <q>That true Religion and pleaſing of God ſtandeth not in making, ſetting up, painting, guilding, cloathing, and decking of dumb and dead Images, nor in kiſſing of them,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50235:13"/>
capping, kneeling, offering to them, incenſing of them, ſetting up of Candles, hanging up of legs, arms, or whole bodies of Wax before them, or praying and asking of of them, or of Saints, things belonging only to God to give; but that all theſe things, be vain and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and moſt damnable before God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Had my Adverſary conſider'd all this, we might won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how he could harden his forehead and Conſcience ſo, as to pretend to the World, that there is an <hi>agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> between the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Oijrs</hi> as to this point; he might as well have pretended to reconcile the moſt palpable falſehood to the cleareſt Truth, ſuch a Diametrical and manifeſt oppoſition there is between the two Churches; the one allowing not only the ſetting up of Images, but the <hi>Honouring, Reverencing</hi> and <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping</hi> of them too, and that ſometimes with the <hi>higheſt</hi> and <hi>ſupreme</hi> Worſhip; and the other profeſſing ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they are ſo far from being <hi>Worſhipped, Adored,</hi> or <hi>Honoured,</hi> that in regard of the horrible dangers and ſins they lead men into, are to be pulled <hi>down</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed</hi> rather.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us now conſider a little the proofs he brings of this pretended agreement. 1. He tells us of ſome Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures in the Church at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and of ſome emble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical repreſentations in the New Church at St. <hi>James</hi>'s, and eſpecially of ſome Pictures in ſome of our New Common-Prayer Books. (He means, I ſuppoſe, not the large Liturgies on our reading Desks, but ſome little Prayer-books in ſome private hands.) A ſtout argument<hi>!</hi> as if what is done by connivance, and by ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons upon their own private Heads, ought to be look't upon as the publick act of our whole Church; or as if there were the ſame danger of Idolatry in <hi>every</hi> age, which hath been in <hi>ſome;</hi> or as if all They who are for <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Ornament,</hi> were agreed with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who are for the moſt intollerable Superſtition.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:50235:13"/>
2. Then he tells us of an injunction given by K. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Sixth to the Clergy (when the Reformation, by the way, was green) that they ſhould inſtruct the people, <hi>that Images ſerve for Remembrance,</hi> &amp;c. But here the man plays a <hi>double</hi> Trick; firſt he renders the place <hi>wrong,</hi> for the words are<hi>—admoniſhing their Pariſhoners, that Images ſerve for no other purpoſe but to be a Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance:</hi> And beſides he <hi>conceals</hi> a moſt <hi>material</hi> paſſage which goes immediately before and after in the ſame Injunction, and it is this; <q>That <hi>ſuch</hi> Images as they (the Clergy) know in any of their Cures to be or to have been abuſed with Pilgrimage or offering of any thing made thereunto, or ſhall be hereafter cenſed unto, they (and none other private perſons) ſhall for the avoiding of that moſt deteſtable offence of <hi>Idolatry</hi> forthwith take down, or cauſe to be taken down, and deſtroy the ſame; and ſhall ſuffer from henceforth no Torches nor Candles, Tapers or Images of Wax to be ſet afore any Image or Picture, but only two Lights upon the high Altar, before the Sacrament, which for the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication that Chriſt is the very true Light of the World, they ſhall ſuffer to remain ſtill; admoniſhing their Pariſhoners, that Images ſerve for no other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe but to be a Remembrance, whereby men may be admoniſhed of the holy Lives and Converſations of them that the ſaid Images do repreſent; which Images if they do abuſe for any other intent, they commit I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry in the ſame, to the great danger of their Souls.</q> And now is not here an admirable agreement between our Church, and the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. As to the main point in Controverſie between us, <hi>viz.</hi> concerning the Honour and Veneration given to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, Kiſſing of them, Kneeling, Praying before them, and in one word, <hi>Worſhipping</hi> of them, (which I have ſhew'd to be the practice of the <hi>Romaniſts)</hi> my Adverſary has the ſtrange confidence to ſay, <hi>pag.</hi> 14. that <hi>the Church</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:50235:14"/>
               <hi>of</hi> England <hi>ſeems to concur with the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>in all this point.</hi> For proof of this moſt important mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he cites. 1. The <hi>30th.</hi> of King <hi>James</hi> his conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; about the <hi>Sign</hi> of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and (and not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat the words at length) any man may ſee the meaning of that place to be this; that though the <hi>Jews</hi> hated the name of the Croſs, yet the inſpir'd Apoſtles honour'd it ſo far, as that they uſed the word equivocally, ſignifying thereby ſometimes Chriſt himſelf, together with the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and merits of his Paſſion; and that the name of the Croſs was ſo honourable, that even in the Apoſtles days, Chriſtians had an honourable eſteem of the Sign of the Croſs. And what of all this? Can this poſſibly argue any kind opinion in the Church of <hi>England</hi> of Venerating, Kiſſing, Incenſing, Bowing down to <hi>Images?</hi> Doth it juſtifie ſo much as the <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> uſe of the Sign of the Croſs it <hi>ſelf?</hi> Doth not our Church confeſs plainly a little after in the very ſame Canon, <hi>That in proceſs of time the ſign of the Croſs was grievouſly abuſed in the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after the ſtain and corruption of Popery had ſpread it ſelf over it?</hi> What mean, what miſerable ſtuff is this, eſpecially for ſuch a <hi>diſcerning,</hi> ſuch a <hi>ſubſtantial Comba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant</hi> as my Adverſary would be thought, to offer unto the World for an Argument. 2. But then miſtruſting the weakneſs of all this, he lays his chief ſtreſs upon a paſſage in our learned <hi>Montague,</hi> where he ſays, there is a Reſpect due unto, and Honour given relatively to the Pictures of Chriſt, the bleſſed Virgin, and Saints; and ſpeaking in the Plural Number, he ſays, <hi>we give it too,</hi> meaning as well as the Papiſts. And what then? doth he ſpeak of any <hi>Publick</hi> reſpect to Pictures in <hi>Churches?</hi> Or of any <hi>other</hi> reſpect then what the <hi>Preſerving</hi> of them amounts to, where there is no <hi>danger</hi> of Idolatry? If my Adverſary be ſo ſenſeleſs as to imagine this, I will refer him to the beginning of that <hi>Chapter</hi> which he cites; for there Mr. <hi>Montague</hi> tells his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Appeal c.</hi> 21.</note>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:50235:14"/>
the <hi>Informers,</hi> that though they would make men believe, that he intended a Religious reſpect and Pious honour to be due to Pictures, and ſo to draw on unto a downright worſhip of them, yet this was not his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; no, he was in that caſe as jealous of Gods Honour, as any gloyting Puritan in the Pack.</p>
            <p>My Adverſary may obſerve, that Mr. <hi>Montague</hi> doth here diſtinguiſh (as I do) <hi>Reſpect</hi> from <hi>Religious</hi> reſpect, and Honour from <hi>Pious</hi> Honour, and then diſtinguiſhes <hi>both</hi> from <hi>Image-Worſhip.</hi> And though he is pleaſed to call this <hi>Cant</hi> in <hi>Me,</hi> yet Mr. <hi>Montague,</hi> to whom he appeals, gives it <hi>another</hi> name, he calls it <hi>Idolatry:</hi> 
               <q>I do not (ſaith he) I cannot, I will not deny, that Idolatry is groſly committed in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 19.</note> The ruder ſort, at leaſt, are not excuſable, who go to it with downright Idolatry, without any Relative adoration, worſhipping that which they beheld with their eyes, the Image of the bleſſed Virgin, <hi>S. Peter, S. Paul,</hi> the Crucifix, as if Chriſt Jeſus were preſent. This Idolatry is ancient in their Schools. <hi>Thomas Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> doth directly vouch it, that the ſame reverence is to be given to the Image of Chriſt, and to Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; whereas therefore Chriſt is adored with the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>Latria,</hi> it follows that his Image is to be adored with the worſhip of <hi>Latria</hi> too: which is now an Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Faith in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and the oppoſite Doctrine flat Hereſie: For ſo <hi>Cabrera</hi> upon that place of <hi>Thomas</hi> writeth; who alledgeth for his purpoſe and opinion, many Old and Later Divines of their School. And <hi>Azorius</hi> the Jeſuit tells us, it is the Conſtant opinion of Divines, that an Image is to be Honour'd with the ſame Honour, and Worſhipped with the ſame Worſhip, that is given to the Object whereof it is the Image.</q> And hence Mr. <hi>Montague</hi> concludes, <hi>Cap.</hi> 22. <q>That Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Practice, and Popiſh Doctrine fetcheth in all, and runneth out into the Extravagant, Idolatrous, Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50235:15"/>
Doctrine of Religious Adoration, either primary or ſecondary, abſolute or reſpective; to that of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Cabrera, Vaſquez,</hi> the Devil and all.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I hope, by this you are ſatisfied that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not in any the leaſt meaſure for an Image-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as this Diſcourſer hath the Confidence to affirm, <hi>pag.</hi> 20. And that in the account I ſent you, I have not abuſed mine own Church, nor expoſed mine <hi>own Church,</hi> nor injured my <hi>Mother,</hi> or any of my Mothers Sons; which was the Principal thing I was to convince you of.</p>
            <p>And now as to what concerns immediately <hi>my ſelf,</hi> I am in compariſon regardleſs: His ill Langague I can pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently bear, and take it for an Honour from a man of his Kidney.</p>
            <p>Yet there are ſome few things more which I muſt take a little notice of for my Vindication. Whereas I told you, 1. That the firſt making of Pictures proceeded partly from Hereticks, the Gnoſticks. 2. That it came chiefly from the fond inclinations of Gentile-Converts. 3. That there was no ſuch thing as the uſe of Images in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Ages. 4. That 'tis contrary to an expreſs Canon of the Council at <hi>Eliberis.</hi> And fifth that in the opinion of <hi>Epiphanius</hi> it is contrary to the Authority of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: This Diſcourſer, not undertaking in the leaſt to <hi>Diſprove</hi> all, or any thing of this, pretends only that <hi>I have ſhot this bolt againſt the Church of</hi> England, and have diſgraced Her, who (as he ſuppoſeth) is for Pictures, and ſo by the conſequence of my Diſcourſe muſt be for that which came from Hereticks, and Heathens; that which was not Primitive; that which is repugnant to Canons; nay indeed, that which is contrary to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: This is his charge againſt me, <hi>pag.</hi> 9, <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>To which, I anſwer; <hi>Firſt,</hi> That what he ſuppoſeth he hath not proved, nor is it true, that the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is fond of Pictures in Churches; the contrary I am
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50235:15"/>
ſure doth plainly appear; nor hath ſhe allowed of them, as far as I know, by any publick Act of Hers, ſince the Reformation. <hi>Secondly,</hi> By looking over the Homily I mention'd, <hi>againſt peril of Idolatry,</hi> by good luck I find thoſe very particular Arguments which this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer cavils at, to be uſed and urged by our Church her ſelf. The Firſt, <hi>pag.</hi> 135, and 137, of the late <hi>Oxford</hi> Edition. The Second She alledgeth at large, <hi>pag.</hi> 120. The Third She ſhews at large throughout the Second Part of that Homily. The Fourth, She cites on her ſide, <hi>pag.</hi> 128. And the Fifth, She urges and makes a large uſe of, <hi>pag.</hi> 116, 117. So that if my angry Adverſary thinks fit to ſtrike the <hi>Second</hi> time, he may think it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable for him to turn his hand from <hi>Me</hi> upon <hi>our Church,</hi> who ſaith the ſame thing; let him ſtrike at Her if he pleaſeth; though I can tell him before-hand, that ſuch blows as <hi>His</hi> will do our Church no harm, let him do his worſt.</p>
            <p>For ſeveral leaves next following, he ſaith nothing but what I have already conſidered. But then <hi>Pag.</hi> 20. He chargeth me for <hi>managing the controverſie with the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts without ever ſtating the Queſtion, or declaring what the Papiſts hold, unbecoming a Scholar.</hi> But he ſhould have conſider'd, that my buſineſs was not to enter into a <hi>Caſuiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> diſpute about the <hi>Lawfulneſs or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfulneſs</hi> of Image-worſhip, but to give an <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> account of matter of <hi>Fact</hi> upon a Queſtion, whether it be an <hi>Innovation,</hi> or No? And <hi>this</hi> was fairly <hi>ſtated;</hi> nay, as far as I perceive by my Adverſary, invincibly <hi>decided;</hi> and I ſhould have thanked him, if inſtead of giving me ſcolding words, and running off from the Point, he had fairly conſider'd and anſwer'd what I had written, like a Scholar, and an ingenuous man, that is not apt to be angry with any one for uſing Books.</p>
            <p>In the next page he asks me, if it be <hi>lawful</hi> for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and Catholicks (as he calls them) to have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50235:16"/>
Reſpect, Honour and Reverence for holy Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, how comes it to be ſo unlawful and abominable for Catholicks to ſignifie and expreſs outwardly this ſame Reſpect, Honour and Reverence, which is ſo <hi>comenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> for all Chriſtians, to have inwardly in their Souls? Certainly that Honour and Reverence which in the Heart is Chriſtian, cannot but be Chriſtian in the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and 'tis very Abſurd to think, a <hi>Duty</hi> can become Idolatry by profeſſing it.</p>
            <p>As to this; 1. I firſt obſerve a ſtrange ſort of Climax; for firſt he expreſſeth it is <hi>lawful</hi> to have an interiour reſpect for Images; then he grows a little, and calls it a <hi>commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable</hi> thing, and at laſt he calls it a <hi>Duty;</hi> whereas if we conſider what he <hi>means</hi> by Reſpect, Honour and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, it is neither <hi>Duty,</hi> nor <hi>commendable,</hi> nor <hi>lawful</hi> (as the caſe may ſtand) to have it for Pictures, and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; nor a Chriſtian thing, either in the Heart, or in the Expreſſion. But Secondly, as to the point it ſelf I muſt ingenuouſly and plainly tell him, that I do not underſtand what ſubſtantial and ſolid grounds <hi>any</hi> man hath to have an interiour Reſpect, Honour and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for Pictures (as Pictures, and as <hi>diſtinct</hi> things from other Furniture and Garniture of a Church, where they are:) I am very confident, that the Ancient Chriſtians had no ſuch interiour Reſpect, but <hi>hatred</hi> rather; and that, not ſo much upon <hi>Prudential</hi> conſiderations, but upon <hi>neceſſary</hi> reaſons, becauſe ſuch reſpect was thought to be contrary to Gods Law. 2. But then, if weak people will ſo far comply with their own Natures, as to ſuffer their Affections to run out after theſe things, doth it follow that they may <hi>expreſs</hi> their Affections as they <hi>pleaſe?</hi> If the Divine <hi>Law</hi> requires me not to bow down to an Image; or if the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of the thing requires me not to bow, becauſe ſuch Religious Bowing is a Token of my <hi>abſolute Subjection</hi> (which is due to God <hi>alone)</hi> am I not bound to think my ſelf abridged of this my
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50235:16"/>
fondly deſired Liberty? I will put two Caſes which are ſomewhat like the Caſes my Adverſary puts, <hi>pag.</hi> 14. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I had a Reverence and Affection for the Popes <hi>Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio</hi> (which I declare, I have not) would it be lawful for me, in the conſtruction of our Laws, to kiſs his hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Knee, to ſerve him upon my Knee, to crave Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of him, and to ſhew him all the very ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, which I owe my Natural <hi>Prince?</hi> Would not this look like a breach of that Allegiance which is due to the Father of my Country? Certainly no Judges <hi>ought</hi> to excuſe my <hi>Sin</hi> for being ſo <hi>Diſloyal,</hi> nor would any Prince paſs me by uncenſured, for acknowledging a <hi>Rival</hi> in his Country. Or ſuppoſe my Adverſary were a Married Man, and his Wife ſhould have a kind <hi>Reſpect</hi> for another perſon, and <hi>expreſs</hi> that Reſpect after a lewd manner, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this her defence and plea: <q>'Tis true, my dear Husband, I had an interiour Reſpect and Affection for ſuch a man; 'tis true I did expreſs and ſhew my Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to him; but I did this, becauſe he is your Friend, he is your picture, he is like you for all the World: What I did therefore was out of true Reſpects to <hi>you;</hi> I kiſt him, and hugg'd him, and the like; but 'twas out of honour and affection to you; all the Kindneſs and Love I ſhew'd him paſſed to the Prototype, and 'twas for your ſake. I hope you will not call this Adultery, becauſe I did it out of Reſpect to you; no, 'tis not Adultery; 'tis only Honour and Veneration to your Image. What if a fellow in the Neighbourhood calls this Adultery? He is a man not to be believed, though he urgeth ſuch a Commandment in the Bible. He is one of a Factious Temper, a multiplier of needleſs Contentions, a blind Combatant, a Trifler, a furious One, a ſingular Illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, one that 'tis uncertain what Church he is of, and the only thing certain is, that he is <hi>no Papiſt;</hi> he is <hi>no Papiſt,</hi> Husband; but a Canting man, that diſputes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a <hi>word. Adultery</hi> he calls it, but 'tis not ſo; 'tis
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50235:17"/>
                  <hi>Reſpect,</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> to <hi>you.</hi> But he is <hi>no Papiſt;</hi> if he were, he would be of another mind, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was for your ſake, and out of Interiour Reſpect to you, that this was done.</q> Suppoſing this, I ſay, I will leave it to my Adverſary to conſider ſeriouſly with himſelf, whether he would accept of this as a fair and reaſonable Excuſe; deſiring him to apply it, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that <hi>Idolatry</hi> is compared in Scripture to <hi>Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi> and <hi>Fornication;</hi> if he has not quite <hi>forgotten</hi> the Book among ſo many <hi>Legends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He taxeth me for treating the Second <hi>Nicene</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil with abuſive Language, becauſe I ſaid, <hi>they were a pack of</hi> Greeks, <hi>that were neither the Wiſeſt, nor the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſteſt men in the World.</hi> Had I ſaid this without ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient grounds, or could this Diſcourſer prove I had Miſ-repreſented them, I were to blame. But whoever ſhall impartially conſider the proceedings of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, I believe will ſoon be of my opinion; for the thing proves <hi>it ſelf.</hi> If my Language doth not pleaſe him, it is not half ſo much as the Three Hundred Fathers at <hi>Frankford</hi> beſtowed upon them, as he may ſee by the <hi>Caroline</hi> Books; out of which the Church of <hi>England</hi> calls them an <hi>Arrogant, Fooliſh,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Council.</hi> If I ſay they eſtabliſht Image-worſhip, it is no more then what <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Second Part of the Homily</hi> againſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril of Idolatry.</note> all the World knows, and <hi>Hinemarus</hi> ſaid the ſame thing, who lived near that time, and knew enough of the matter. And if they be Ridiculous, my Adverſary may thank <hi>Them</hi> for it; they made <hi>Themſelves</hi> ſo. Some of their Arguments I induſtriouſly conceal'd, becauſe they are ſo very ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, that I fancied my Relating of them would not be Believed.</p>
            <p>He pretends, <hi>pag.</hi> 31. That the reaſon why Images were not uſed in the Primitive Ages was, <hi>becauſe it was Inexpedient and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſeaſonable, Chriſtians then living a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:50235:17"/>
               <hi>Pagans and Jews.</hi> But if he pleaſeth to conſult <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus, Origen,</hi> and other of the Primitive Writers (who knew their own reaſons beſt) he will find, that they inſiſted not upon the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſeaſonableneſs,</hi> but upon the <hi>unlawfulneſs</hi> of having Images, becauſe they thought it contrary to Gods Commandments.</p>
            <p>I wonder the man ſhould ſo much as <hi>pretend</hi> not to underſtand <hi>(pag.</hi> 34.) how Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Second contradicted <hi>Gregory</hi> the Firſt. But now I think on't, he is not apt to believe his <hi>Senſes:</hi> For the thing is as clear as the Sun to any one that can <hi>Read,</hi> and will truſt his <hi>Eyes,</hi> that <hi>Gregory</hi> the Firſt wrote <hi>againſt</hi> Image-worſhip, and the Second of that name wrote <hi>for</hi> it. And though the Latter endeavour'd to excuſe himſelf and his party with this pretence, <hi>That they did not worſhip Images as Gods,</hi> yet my Adverſary knows that the old Heathens ſaid the ſame thing; and therefore this could no more acquit this Pope, than it could the <hi>Pagans</hi> from the charge of Idolatry.</p>
            <p>He pretends I am kind to the Heathens; as if my meaning was <hi>to excuſe them from Idolatry, ſo the better to fix this crime upon the Papiſts,</hi> and hereupon he makes a long Harangue. The very truth is, I never intended to excuſe <hi>either,</hi> or take off the Load from one to lay it upon the other. But this I ſay, (and the thing is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt) that upon the ſame grounds that the Romaniſts juſtifie <hi>Their</hi> worſhipping of Images, the old Heathens juſtified <hi>Theirs.</hi> And leſt I ſhould be thought, a <hi>ſingular Illuminate,</hi> ſhould I make a compariſon between both (as to that) I ſay further, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> her ſelf hath long ago done a great deal <hi>more</hi> of that kind then I am willing to do at this time of day. In the Third part of the Homily, I mention'd before, She hath at large compared the Idolatry of the one, with the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry of the other, both as to the Images <hi>themſelves,</hi> and as
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50235:18"/>
to the <hi>manner</hi> of worſhipping them. I refer you to the place, beſeeching you to read it, not for your <hi>Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> only, but for your <hi>diverſion</hi> and <hi>pleaſure</hi> too.</p>
            <p>After this it is inſinuated, <hi>pag.</hi> 37. That I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed not only the <hi>Credit,</hi> but the very <hi>Being</hi> of our Church in a manner, our <hi>Ordination,</hi> our <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> our <hi>Authority of Preaching;</hi> and all this, by my writing a poor Pamphlet againſt Image-worſhip. A man of Senſe would wonder at the conſequence; but the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it ſeems is, becauſe our Church was once in Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo that if the one be <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> the other muſt <hi>Ceaſe.</hi> But my Adverſary knows our principle to be this, That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is really a Church (as to the <hi>Eſſentials</hi> of a Church) though a very <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſound</hi> and <hi>Corrupt</hi> one as to Her additions; and how our Communion with that Church could bring ſuch a Contagion as can Un-Church us, is a thing which we cannot underſtand. But this, among ſome other mean conſiderations which are now objected againſt <hi>Me,</hi> have been objected formerly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my <hi>good Friend,</hi> and have been abundantly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd at the end of his Excellent <hi>Defence;</hi> and becauſe I am not willing this Pamphlet ſhould ſwell with things, ſaid over again, I refer you to that piece, where you will find this, and ſome other cavils fully anſwer'd, which are ſcatteringly thrown by this Diſcourſer, about <hi>bowing towards the Altar, and at the name of Jeſus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Next follows (which I believe was the <hi>Principal</hi> thing intended by my Adverſary) a ſly and artificial Application to our <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> as if <hi>they</hi> had the ſame reaſon to depart from <hi>our</hi> Church, as <hi>we</hi> had to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Now the reaſon of our departure was, becauſe we could not poſſibly continue any longer in the Communion of that Church, without being <hi>knowingly</hi> guilty of many damnable Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50235:18"/>
and Sins. If this be the caſe between <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and our diſſenting Brethren I will depart from the Church of <hi>England</hi> to morrow, though not to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But, God be thanked, all reaſonable men are convinced, that the caſe is not the ſame. And my Adverſary is malicious and vain in ſaying <hi>pag.</hi> 38. That <hi>Since the greateſt part of thoſe things upon which the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent is founded, are ſuch as have been inſtituted and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>why ſhould the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters receive them from the Church of</hi> England, <hi>whilſt theſe ſame Church-Guides, who preſs the obſervance, take ſo much pains to prove thoſe from whom they receiv'd them, to be Idolaters?</hi> What? Did the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> Inſtitute thoſe things whereon the <hi>Diſſent</hi> is founded? I think they may be Idolaters to the Worlds end, and yet our Conſtitutions remain unſpotted. Was the <hi>Epiſcopal Government</hi> Inſtituted by the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> Was our <hi>Liturgy</hi> compiled by the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> Was the Sign of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and a few more of our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervances Inſtituted by the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> This is a vanity to be deſpiſed; and upon this Point I will Engage in a Controverſie with this Diſcourſer, when he pleaſes or dares. In the mean time I take the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to tell him, that his <hi>Trick</hi> will not <hi>Take;</hi> all of Us are ſenſible what the <hi>meaning</hi> of this is, and who they are that ſtand behind the Curtain to inflame us, to ſet us at further variance with one another, to drive on a <hi>Third</hi> intereſt, and at laſt to laugh at our folly, if we can be made to ſerve it.</p>
            <p>In the Concluſion of all my Adverſary gives me a gentle lick: for reflecting upon Me, and the Letter I ſent you, he ſays, <hi>the Author is to be excuſed; the whole is nothing more then a Letter: and every body knows, that a Letter, however proper it may be to the perſon to whom 'tis directed, is many times very abſur'd when 'tis divulg'd</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:50235:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>and made Common; we'll Excuſe therefore the Writer, but really he is to blame that Publiſh't it.</hi> To this I anſwer in a few words; that if this Diſcourſer and his Party will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give me the <hi>writing</hi> of that Letter, I know you will forgive him that <hi>Publiſht</hi> it, and I believe all conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and honeſt men will forgive us <hi>Both,</hi> and as for this <hi>Diſcourſer,</hi> whatever his Sin is, he knows I ſuppoſe where to have a pardon <hi>too,</hi> if he has but <hi>Money.</hi> I am, Sir</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Moſt Faithful and Obedient Servant.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July <hi>26th.</hi> 1687.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
